Inventory of the Charles Andrew Willoughby papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Charles Andrew Willoughby papers
1945-1962
61013
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes, 1 album box, 1 envelope, 1 sound recording, (1.5 linear feet)
Drafts, reports, correspondence, newsletters, printed matter, and a sound recording relating to the World War II campaigns of General Douglas MacArthur in the Pacific, the Richard Sorge espionage case, the anti-communist movement in the United States, Cold War defense needs of the United States, and Japanese rearmament.
Willoughby, Charles Andrew, 1892-1972
Access
Collection open for research.
Use copies of all sound recordings in this collection are available. For access to any video recordings or motion picture film in this collection, please contact the Hoover Institution Archives.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1961.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1892: Born, Heidelberg, Germany
1910: Immigrated to the United States; enlisted in the United States Army, 5th Infantry
1914: Received Bachelor of Arts, Gettysburg College; commissioned a second lieutenant in the Officers' Volunteer Corps of the United States Army
1917: Joined the American Expeditionary Force as a captain
1936: Promoted to lieutenant colonel
1942: Named chief of staff for Intelligence under General MacArthur's staff for the Southwest Pacific Area
1951: Retired from the military
1972: Died, Naples, Florida
Scope and Content of Collection
Drafts, reports, correspondence, newsletters, printed matter and a sound recording relating to the World War II campaigns of General Douglas MacArthur in the Pacific, the Richard Sorge espionage case, the anti-communist movement in the United States, Cold War defense needs of the United States, and Japanese rearmament.
MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964.; Sorge, Richard, 1895-1944.; United States. Army--Officers.; Anti-communist movements--United States.; Communism.; East Asia.; Espionage, Russian--East Asia.; Japan--Defenses.; Japan.; Phonorecords.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union.; United States--Armed Forces.; United States--Defenses.; United States--Politics and government.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Pacific Ocean.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Biographical File, 1950
  - Army and Navy Legion of Honor membership announcement, 1950 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Honorary dinner menu, 1950 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - National Sojourners honorary membership certificate, undated (Box-folder 1: 3)
- The Anti-Communist Movement File, 1945-1962
  - Legal documents, 1958, 1960
    - Un-American Committee hearings, 1958, 1960 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Periodicals, 1957-1962
    - American Mercury, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 1: 5-8)
    - Up Ye Dead, undated (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - The Weekly Crusader, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - General, 1961, undated (Box-folder 1: 11)
- Correspondence, 1945-1960 (Box-folder 1: 12)
- World War II - Southwest Pacific Area Campaign File, 1944-1946
  - Printed matter, 1946
    - "Index to ATIS Publications,", 1946 (Box-folder 1: 13-14, Box-folder 2: 1-2)
    - "The Return Of MacArthur,", undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Research reports, 1944-1945
    - "Allied Prisoners of War in Japanese Hands - Allied Translator and Interpreter Section South West Pacific Area,", 1945 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - "Defects Arising from the Doctrine of 'Spiritual Superiority' as Factors in Japanese Military Psychology - Allied Translator and Interpreter Section South West Pacific Area,", 1945 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - "The Exploitation of Japanese Documents - Allied Translator and Interpreter Section South West Pacific Area,", 1944 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - "Japanese Violations of the Laws of War - Allied Translator and Interpreter Section South West Pacific Area,", 1945 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - "The Pearl Harbor Operation - Allied Translator and Interpreter Section South West Pacific Area,", 1945 (Box-folder 2: 5)
- Printed Matter, 1957-1961
  - Foreign Intelligence Digest, 1957-1961 (Box-folder 2: 6)
- Richard Sorge Espionage Case File, 1945-1961
  - Printed Matter
    - "A Partial Documentation of the Sorge Espionage Case,", 1950 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Speeches and writings
    - Richard Sorge case drafts
      - Partial Draft, undated (Box-folder 3: 2)
      - Notes prepared by Richard Sorge in lieu of a statement, Tokyo District Criminal Court, undated (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - Manuscripts
      - Soviet American Spy Ring Part II: Smedley and Associates, complete manuscript, undated (Box-folder 3: 4)
      - Soviet American Spy Ring Part II: Smedley and Associates, incomplete manuscript, undated (Box-folder 3: 5)
        General note
        Part I missing (only 4 typed copies made of part 1).
    - Research notes, 1945-1961
      - The Sorge espionage case, Shanghai, Tokyo, New York, 1941-1951 (Box-folder 3: 6)
- General Willoughby Sound Recording, 1951 September 4
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Use copy reference number: 61013_a_0002844
  Scope and Contents note
  Willoughby speaks on the future of Japan and what it means for the future of Asia and the Pacific area. 1 sound disc.
- Photographs, 1945-1962 (Envelope envelope)
- Collection of Japanese War Paintings, 1947